<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" media="screen" href="/~d/styles/rss2full.xsl"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" media="screen" href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~d/styles/itemcontent.css"?><rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:feedburner="http://rssnamespace.org/feedburner/ext/1.0" version="2.0">

<channel>
	<title>Popehat</title>
	
	<link>http://www.popehat.com</link>
	<description>A Group Complaint about Law, Liberty, and Leisure</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2014 16:39:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
		<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
		<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	
	<atom10:link xmlns:atom10="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/Popehat" /><feedburner:info uri="popehat" /><atom10:link xmlns:atom10="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" rel="hub" href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" /><item>
		<title>From the "lol journalism" Files:  No, The Defamation Case Against Courtney Love Will Not Change Twitter</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Popehat/~3/-fhCx_5ZswM/</link>
		<comments>http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/17/from-the-lol-journalism-files-no-the-defamation-case-against-courtney-love-will-not-change-twitter/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2014 16:39:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ken White]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Free Speech]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Journalism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.popehat.com/?p=21354</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[An appalling large percentage of journalism about the legal system sucks. There are exceptions &#8212; there are legal journalists I respect, who take pains to get it right &#8212; but for the most part the media gets coverage of both criminal and civil cases badly wrong. (I am aware of Gell-Mann Amnesia and therefore please [&#8230;]<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/17/from-the-lol-journalism-files-no-the-defamation-case-against-courtney-love-will-not-change-twitter/">From the "lol journalism" Files:  No, The Defamation Case Against Courtney Love Will Not Change Twitter</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>An appalling large percentage of journalism about the legal system sucks.</p>
<p>There are exceptions &#8212; there are legal journalists I respect, who take pains to get it right &#8212; but for the most part the media gets coverage of both criminal and civil cases badly wrong.  (I am aware of <a href="http://www.patheos.com/blogs/geneveith/2011/08/the-murray-gell-mann-amnesia-effect/" target="_blank">Gell-Mann Amnesia</a> and therefore please do not infer that I believe other coverage is necessarily more reliable.)  </p>
<p>Case in point:  coverage of a defamation suit against Courtney Love.  <a href="http://gma.yahoo.com/blogs/abc-blogs/courtney-love-defends-tweet-39-twibel-39-defamation-132507418--abc-news-celebrities.html?vp=1" target="_blank">Take ABC's coverage.</a>  ABC starts with this:</p>
<blockquote><p>For the first time, a case of alleged libel on Twitter is going to trial </p></blockquote>
<p>Really?  Twitter was launched in 2006.  ABC repeats this claim &#8212; that no defamation case about a statement on Twitter has ever gone to trial &#8212; but I'm skeptical.  How did they research that?  How did they determine that, across the United States, no case about Twitter defamation has ever gone to trial?  Do they assume, incorrectly, that any such trial would result in a published decision that would make it easy to find a record of the trial?  Are they just repeating what other media outlets say in conclusory fashion?  Moreover, why is the assertion <em>significant?</em>  Does ABC mean to imply that the trial represents the first time the legal system has had to confront allegations of defamation in Twitter?  If so, ABC is wrong.  It took me 30 seconds on Westlaw to find a dozen court opinions (both courts of appeal and federal district courts) analyzing defamation claims premised on Twitter content.    </p>
<blockquote><p>A handful of Twitter libel, or Twibel, cases have been filed in the past, but Love's case is the only one that has made it to trial in the U.S.</p></blockquote>
<p>Again!  First, "Twibel" is not a legal thing; ABC, stop trying to make it a thing.  Second, I'm not sure what ABC thinks a "handful" is.  It took me 30 seconds to find more than a dozen cases on Westlaw involving allegations of Twitter defamation&#8211; that those are only the cases that <em>generated a written opinion that was submitted to Westlaw.</em>  The vast majority of state trial-court cases would generate no such written order.  What's ABC's basis for saying that only a "handful" of cases have been filed?  Is that just null-content filler?</p>
<blockquote><p>"The Courtney Love Twitter lawsuit is monumental because the judge has now determined that tweeting in California can potentially give rise to liability under the theory of defamation," attorney Brian Claypool said, who is not affiliated with this case.</p></blockquote>
<p>Either ABC misquoted Brian Claypool, or else Claypool is not affiliated with logic or reality either.  Libel is written defamation.  Twitter is written.  There is nothing about Twitter that logically calls into question whether something written there can be defamatory.  ABC's implication to the contrary is nonsense.  </p>
<blockquote><p>"The Courtney Love case will set a precedent that will result in, potentially, the average person being liable as well," Claypool added.</p></blockquote>
<p>No it won't.  First, a trial in the trial court doesn't "set a precedent" in the way Mr. Claypool and ABC are suggesting.  Published opinions by trial and appellate courts set legal precedents.  Moreover, nothing about the Courtney Love case has the potential to establish a "precedent" regarding whether or not things written on Twitter are written, and therefore potentially defamation, because that was never in question by anyone minimally familiar with the law.</p>
<blockquote><p>This case could also re-write the rules for the much-loved celebrity Twitter wars that have made headlines over the years: Miley Cyrus vs. Sinead O'Connor and Demi Lovato vs. Perez Hilton just to name two.</p></blockquote>
<p>No, ABC, you ignorance-promoting cesspool of mediocrity, it couldn't.</p>
<p>Now, there is a grain of relevant law in this abysmally reported story:</p>
<blockquote><p>Love, 49, took the witness stand Wednesday and said the tweet was merely an opinion, that the Internet is full of hyperbole and exaggeration. </p></blockquote>
<p>And that's the relevant legal issue in the case, which ABC misses almost entirely, and doesn't explain to its readers.  </p>
<p>As I often talk about here, <a href="http://www.popehat.com/2012/07/06/cartoonist-donna-barstow-engages-in-modern-online-version-of-hey-guys-watch-this/" target="_blank">statements of opinion are not defamatory and are protected by the First Amendment so long as they are based on known or disclosed facts.</a>  In other words, if I say "Courtney Love sounds like that Edvard Munch painting looks," that's pure opinion and can't be defamation.  If I say "Courtney Love's article on Huffington Post about healing amputations with fresh arugula and Pilates makes her sound like a quack and an idiot," that's pure protected opinion.  If I said "Courtney Love committed fraud," that might or might not be protected opinion, depending on whether (1) a court determined it was a statement of fact versus a statement of hyperbole and rhetoric, and (2) a court determined it was an opinion based on disclosed facts, or a statement about undisclosed facts.  If I linked to an article about Love's conduct and said "Courtney Love committed fraud" that's opinion based on disclosed facts," if I say "I did business with Courtney Love and, without telling you any details, she committed fraud," that may be a statement of fact, because it's not based on established or disclosed facts.</p>
<p>Context is relevant to that determination.  California courts, in particular, have suggested that expression online is more likely to be taken as hyperbole or opinion rather than a statement of literal fact subject to defamation analysis.  As one court put it in 2012:</p>
<blockquote><p> In determining statements are nonactionable opinions, a number of recent cases have relied heavily on the fact that statements were made in Internet forums. . . . With respect to statements posted in a section of the Craigslist Web site entitled “Rants and Raves,” the court in <em>Summit Bank</em> found that a reader “should be predisposed to view them with a certain amount of skepticism, and with an understanding that they will likely present one-sided viewpoints rather than assertions of provable facts. ‘[A]ny reader familiar with the culture of &#8230; most electronic bulletin boards &#8230; would know that board culture encourages discussion participants to play fast and loose with facts&#8230;. Indeed, the very fact that most of the posters remain anonymous, or pseudonymous, is a cue to discount their statements accordingly.’ [Citations.]” (Summit Bank, supra, 206 Cal.App.4th at pp. 696–697, 142 Cal.Rptr.3d 40.) . . . .  Like the court in <em>Summit Bank</em>, the court in <em>Krinsky</em> relied in large part on the fact the statements were made on an Internet message board where heated discussions about the plaintiff were taking place. (Id. at pp. 1175, 1177–1178, 72 Cal.Rptr.3d 231.) . . . As we have noted, the statements about Chaker were made in the context of the paternity and child support litigation going on between Chaker and Wendy's daughter and all were made on Internet Web sites which plainly invited the sort of exaggerated and insulting criticisms of businesses and individuals which occurred here. The overall thrust of the comments attributed is that Chaker is a dishonest and scary person. This overall appraisal of Chaker is on its face nothing more than a negative, but nonactionable opinion.</p>
<p><em>Chaker v. Mateo</em>, 209 Cal. App. 4th 1138, 1148-50 (2012)</p></blockquote>
<p>Put another way, the fact that Courtney Love uttered her written statement on Twitter makes it more likely that a court will view it as hyperbole or opinion, and thus not a statement of fact that is potentially defamatory.  That's not new.  It's established.</p>
<p>So:  the Courtney Love case is not novel or innovative.  It applies established legal principles to rather mundane facts.  ABC (and other media outlets) could have used it as a springboard to discuss basic free speech principles, but instead uses it breathlessly to promote ignorance.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/17/from-the-lol-journalism-files-no-the-defamation-case-against-courtney-love-will-not-change-twitter/">From the "lol journalism" Files:  No, The Defamation Case Against Courtney Love Will Not Change Twitter</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
 <img src="http://www.popehat.com/?feed-stats-post-id=21354" width="1" height="1" style="display: none;" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/17/from-the-lol-journalism-files-no-the-defamation-case-against-courtney-love-will-not-change-twitter/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/17/from-the-lol-journalism-files-no-the-defamation-case-against-courtney-love-will-not-change-twitter/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Update:  The Quantum of Recovery For Rape-and-Torture-By-Police In New Mexico Is $1.6 Million</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Popehat/~3/luU0I957Z-U/</link>
		<comments>http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/16/update-the-quantum-of-recovery-for-rape-and-torture-by-police-in-new-mexico-is-1-6-million/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2014 02:27:12 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ken White]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effluvia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cops]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Criminal Justice]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.popehat.com/?p=21346</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Back in November I wrote about David Eckert of New Mexico. As you may recall, City of Deming police officers stopped Eckert for running a stop sign, and together with Hidalgo County Sheriff's Deputies concluded that there was probable cause to think that he was smuggling drugs in his anus. As I wrote back then, [&#8230;]<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/16/update-the-quantum-of-recovery-for-rape-and-torture-by-police-in-new-mexico-is-1-6-million/">Update:  The Quantum of Recovery For Rape-and-Torture-By-Police In New Mexico Is $1.6 Million</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2013/11/07/what-is-the-quantum-of-proof-necessary-for-police-to-rape-and-torture-you-in-new-mexico/" target="_blank">Back in November I wrote about David Eckert of New Mexico</a>.  As you may recall, City of Deming police officers stopped Eckert for running a stop sign, and together with Hidalgo County Sheriff's Deputies concluded that there was probable cause to think that he was smuggling drugs in his anus.  As I wrote back then, that conclusion was based on the following fanciful chain of supposition:</p>
<blockquote><p>
    That his hands were shaking and he avoided eye contact during a traffic stop;</p>
<p>    He refused to consent to a search of his person;</p>
<p>    He stood erect with his legs together;</p>
<p>    No drugs were found in his car or in a pat-down of him (police pat-downs for weapons often turn up drugs, which mysteriously feel like dangerous weapons when touched by police, or which are immediately identifiable as drugs when touched by police);</p>
<p>    A drug dog (with no information given about the dog's training or qualifications or success rate) "alerted" to his car seat (though no drugs were found in his car); and</p>
<p>    An unidentified Hidalgo County K-9 officer asserted, without any specificity, that Eckert had previously hidden drugs in his anus.
</p></blockquote>
<p>Based on those "facts," and with the approval of Deputy District Attorney Daniel Dougherty, the police sought and obtained a warrant to search Mr. Eckert's anus.  The following rape and torture &#8212; and I use those words deliberately and advisedly &#8212; followed:</p>
<blockquote><p>    1. Eckert's abdominal area was x-rayed; no narcotics were found.</p>
<p>    2. Doctors then performed an exam of Eckert's anus with their fingers; no narcotics were found.</p>
<p>    3. Doctors performed a second exam of Eckert's anus with their fingers; no narcotics were found.</p>
<p>    4. Doctors penetrated Eckert's anus to insert an enema. Eckert was forced to defecate in front of doctors and police officers. Eckert watched as doctors searched his stool. No narcotics were found.</p>
<p>    5. Doctors penetrated Eckert's anus to insert an enema a second time. Eckert was forced to defecate in front of doctors and police officers. Eckert watched as doctors searched his stool. No narcotics were found.</p>
<p>    6. Doctors penetrated Eckert's anus to insert an enema a third time. Eckert was forced to defecate in front of doctors and police officers. Eckert watched as doctors searched his stool. No narcotics were found.</p>
<p>    7. Doctors then x-rayed Eckert again; no narcotics were found.</p>
<p>    8. Doctors prepared Eckert for surgery, sedated him, and then performed a colonoscopy where a scope with a camera was inserted into Eckert's anus, rectum, colon, and large intestines. No narcotics were found.</p></blockquote>
<p>No.  No narcotics were found.</p>
<p>Are there consequences to that sort of conduct?  Sort of.  Eckert has settled with the City of Deming, the County of Hidalgo, Officers Bobby Orosco and Robert Chavez, and Deputies David Arredondo, Patrick Green and Robert Rodriguez.  He has agreed to <a href="http://www.popehat.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/Eckert-Dismissal.pdf">dismiss</a> his <a href="http://www.popehat.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/Eckert-Dismissal-2.pdf">lawsuit</a> against them.  <a href="http://kdvr.com/2014/01/16/new-mexico-police-to-pay-1-6-million-after-forcing-man-to-undergo-anal-procedures/" target="_blank">he will be paid $1.6 million</a> &#8212; it's not clear how that is apportioned between the City and the County, but you can assume that New Mexico taxpayers, not the law enforcement officers who engaged in a conspiracy to commit torture and rape, will foot the bill.</p>
<p>Deputy District Attorney Daniel Dougherty has a <a href="http://www.popehat.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/Dougherty-Dismiss-Motion.pdf">motion to dismiss pending.</a>  He will probably win it.  Prosecutorial immunity is most likely broad enough, under current law, to cover approving a transparently ridiculous warrant application seeking to torture and rape a man based on fluff.  Nice work if you can get it and you are in to that sort of thing, I suppose.</p>
<p>Doctor Robert Wilcox of the Gila Medical Center &#8212; <a href="http://www.popehat.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/Wilcox-Opposition.pdf">who played the "bring out the gimp" role in this rape and torture scenario</a> &#8212; has <a href="http://www.popehat.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/Wilcox-Dismiss.pdf">also filed a motion to dismiss,</a> which in part argues that he is entitled to immunity because he was following orders &#8212; the orders of the police and the judicially approved search warrant.  We'll see how that works out for him.</p>
<p>The $1.6 million was offered and accepted quite swiftly.  That's a substantial amount of money for a case not involving death or dismemberment, especially during times when local governments don't have a lot of money.  It suggests to me that the City and County thought they had a terrible case.  It makes me even more suspicious that the key "fact" of the warrant application &#8212; that some unspecified deputy told the affiant that Mr. Eckert had smuggled drugs in his anus at some unspecified time before &#8212; was knowingly fabricated by somebody in the chain.  </p>
<p>This case sickened me.  But I can't say that it surprised me.  The only thing out of it that would surprise me is if any of the individual police officers or sheriff's deputies faced any genuine significant consequences arising from it.</p>
<p>Whether or not you agree with my legal criticism of the sufficiency of the warrant application, bear this in mind:  because of the mindset promoted by the Great War on Drugs, these cops, this deputy DA, this judge, and this doctor all reached the same moral conclusion.  Their moral conclusion was that because they posited that this man had drugs in his anus &#8212; necessarily the small amount that could fit there &#8212; it was necessary and appropriate and acceptable forcibly and repeatedly to probe his anus, forcibly to give him an enema, to x-ray him, to sedate him, and to perform a colonoscopy on him under sedation.  That's the mindset of the Great War on Drugs.  It's perverted and despicable.  It's subhuman.  Do you support it?  </p>
<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/16/update-the-quantum-of-recovery-for-rape-and-torture-by-police-in-new-mexico-is-1-6-million/">Update:  The Quantum of Recovery For Rape-and-Torture-By-Police In New Mexico Is $1.6 Million</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
 <img src="http://www.popehat.com/?feed-stats-post-id=21346" width="1" height="1" style="display: none;" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/16/update-the-quantum-of-recovery-for-rape-and-torture-by-police-in-new-mexico-is-1-6-million/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>36</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/16/update-the-quantum-of-recovery-for-rape-and-torture-by-police-in-new-mexico-is-1-6-million/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Roger Shuler Convicted of Resisting Arrest, Remains In Custody for Contempt of Prior Restraint Order</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Popehat/~3/-kp8uBuWZ6o/</link>
		<comments>http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/15/roger-shuler-convicted-of-resisting-arrest-remains-in-custody-for-contempt-of-prior-restraint-order/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2014 19:46:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ken White]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effluvia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Criminal Justice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Free Speech]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Roger Shuler]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.popehat.com/?p=21341</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I've previously written about Roger Shuler, the Alabama blogger currently in jail for contempt of court based on his defiance of an injunction that is likely an unconstitutional prior restraint of speech. Though I think that Shuler's history shows him to be a vexatious litigant, and though I think his erratic and foolish behavior has [&#8230;]<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/15/roger-shuler-convicted-of-resisting-arrest-remains-in-custody-for-contempt-of-prior-restraint-order/">Roger Shuler Convicted of Resisting Arrest, Remains In Custody for Contempt of Prior Restraint Order</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I've previously written about <a href="http://www.popehat.com/tag/roger-shuler/" target="_blank">Roger Shuler,</a> the Alabama blogger currently in jail for contempt of court based on his defiance of an injunction that is likely an unconstitutional prior restraint of speech.  Though I think that <a href="http://www.popehat.com/2013/10/27/alabama-blogger-roger-shuler-arrested-for-violation-of-unconstitutional-injunction/" target="_blank">Shuler's history shows him to be a vexatious litigant,</a> and though I think <a href="http://www.popehat.com/2013/11/17/alabama-court-roger-shuler-continue-to-thwart-roger-shulers-first-amendment-rights/" target="_blank">his erratic and foolish behavior has contributed substantially to this situation,</a> I find the injunction against him and his incarceration for violating it very troubling.  I'm quoted on that point in <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/01/12/us/bloggers-incarceration-raises-first-amendment-questions.html?smid=fb-share" target="_blank">last weekend's New York Times.</a>  </p>
<p>There are some developments of note.</p>
<p><strong><em>Shuler Has Been Convicted of Resisting Arrest And Sentenced to 90 Days Imprisonment, Suspended</em></strong></p>
<p>Roger Shuler was charged with "resisting arrest" (sometimes called "contempt of cop") based on alleged conduct during his arrest in October 2013.  Yesterday he was <a href="http://blog.al.com/spotnews/2014/01/shelby_county_blogger_sentence.html" target="_blank">convicted of resiting arrest and sentenced to 90 days in jail, suspended,</a> after a bench trial (that is, a trial by judge, not by jury) before Shelby County District Judge Ronald Jackson.  I'm not an expert on Alabama criminal procedure, but my rough understanding is that misdemeanors like this are tried by bench trial in the "district courts" of Alabama, and can be appealed to the "circuit court" for a trial by jury, which is a strange way to run a railroad.<a href="http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/15/roger-shuler-convicted-of-resisting-arrest-remains-in-custody-for-contempt-of-prior-restraint-order/#wsa-endnote-1" name="wsa-inline-1"><sup>1</sup></a>  </p>
<p>Three things concern me about Shuler's bench trial.</p>
<p><strong>First</strong>, he represented himself.  It's not clear whether he refused appointed counsel (which he <a href="http://www.cbs42.com/news/jailed-blogger-in-court" target="_blank">foolishly did before</a>) or whether he was somehow deprived of one.  I suspect he refused counsel, which is transcendentally idiotic and self-indulgent.  He <a href="http://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/00-1214" target="_blank">had a right to appointed counsel.</a>  Nothing in his history of pro se litigation suggests he was even minimally competent to defend himself.</p>
<p><strong>Second</strong>, the judge denied Shuler a continuance to gather evidence, which Shuler requested because he had been in custody since October:</p>
<blockquote><p>Jackson denied a request made by Shuler that the case be continued after he claimed that his incarceration prevented him from preparing his defense and obtaining certain discovery material, such as a video recording of the incident and copies of arrest warrants.</p></blockquote>
<p>Now, representing yourself is likely to lead to this sort of result &#8212; you're not prepared for trial.  But judges are supposed to take steps to protect the rights of pro se defendants. The arrest &#8212; and the alleged unlawful resisting of arrest &#8212; is less than three months old, and I find it highly dubious and suspicious that a judge would deny a continuance to give Shuler more time to seek discovery and prepare.</p>
<p><strong>Third</strong>, it's not clear from the reporting how the prosecution proved the elements of the offense.  I'm not talking about my standard skepticism of police claims that a suspect improperly resisted.  I'm talking about proving that the arrest was lawful in the first place.  </p>
<p><a href="http://codes.lp.findlaw.com/alcode/13A/10/2/13A-10-41" target="_blank">Under Alabama law resisting arrest is an attempt to prevent a <em>lawful</em> arrest.</a>  Resisting an unlawful arrest <a href="https://www.courtlistener.com/alacrimapp/aoqK/shinault-v-city-of-huntsville/" target="_blank">is not, as I understand Alabama law, a violation of the resisting arrest statute.</a>  To make a lawful arrest under Alabama law, <a href="http://codes.lp.findlaw.com/alcode/15/10/1/15-10-3" target="_blank">a peace officer must have an arrest warrant, or must have probable cause to believe the suspect committed a felony, or must observe the suspect commit a crime.</a>  Shuler apparently argued at trial that the arresting officer didn't have a warrant and didn't observe any crime, and that therefore the arrest was not lawful and Shuler could not have committed the crime of resisting arrest.  <a href="http://legalschnauzer.blogspot.com/2014/01/roger-shuler-convicted-of-resisting.html" target="_blank">That's what his wife argues now.</a>  Regrettably the news coverage of the brief bench trial <a href="http://blog.al.com/spotnews/2014/01/shelby_county_blogger_sentence.html" target="_blank">doesn't clarify how the prosecution proved (if it did) that the arrest was lawful in the first place.</a> </p>
<p>The district judge imposed a suspended 90-day jail sentence, meaning Shuler is now incarcerated only on the contempt of court.</p>
<p>In short the coverage of the trial leaves me where I was before:  questioning whether the Alabama court system is treating Shuler according to the rule of law, but also suspecting that Shuler is doing everything he can to undermine his own best interests.</p>
<p><strong><em>Shuler Remains Incarcerated On The Contempt of Court Charges</em></strong></p>
<p>Back in November, the Alabama court issued a permanent injunction against Roger Shuler forbidding him from saying certain things about the plaintiffs in his case and requiring him to remove certain posts from his blog.  The court did so after a hearing that it characterized as a "permanent injunction hearing."  <a href="http://www.popehat.com/2013/11/17/alabama-court-roger-shuler-continue-to-thwart-roger-shulers-first-amendment-rights/" target="_blank">As I explained back in November I believe that permanent injunction is a prior restraint in violation of the First Amendment</a>; the cases permitting such prior restraint against defamation generally only do so after a full trial before the correct finder of fact (which should be a jury), not after some mere "hearing."  There's nothing extraordinary about this case that should permit departure from that precedent.  So unless Shuler somehow waived a trial by jury or consented to resolution of the defamation claim at a hearing &#8212; something that's not outside the realm of possibility given his erratic behavior &#8212; the injunction seems unlawful.</p>
<p>Yet Shuler remains in jail for contempt of court based on his refusal to comply with the injunction.  How long can he stay there?  That's complicated.</p>
<p>There are two types of contempt consequences:  punitive and coercive.  Punitive contempt sanctions punish contempt; coercive contempt consequences seek to force someone to do something.  <a href="http://www.law.cornell.edu/supct/html/92-1625.ZO.html" target="_blank">Here's how the Supreme Court described the difference, and the different requirements:</a></p>
<blockquote><p>"Criminal contempt is a crime in the ordinary sense," Bloom v. Illinois, 391 U.S. 194, 201 (1968), and "criminal penalties may not be imposed on someone who has not been afforded the protections that the Constitution requires of such criminal proceedings." Hicks v. Feiock, 485 U.S. 624, 632 (1988). See In re Bradley, 318 U.S. 50 (1943) (double jeopardy); Cooke v. United States, 267 U.S. 517, 537 (1925) (rights to notice of charges, assistance of counsel, summary process, and to present a defense); Gompers v. Bucks Stove &#038; Range Co., 221 U.S. 418, 444 (1911) (privilege against self incrimination, right to proof beyond a reasonable doubt). For "serious" criminal contempts involving imprisonment of more than six months, these protections include the right to jury trial. Bloom, 391 U. S., at 199; see also Taylor v. Hayes, 418 U.S. 488, 495 (1974). In contrast, civil contempt sanctions, or those penalties designed to compel future compliance with a court order, are considered to be coercive and avoidable through obedience, and thus may be imposed in an ordinary civil proceeding upon notice and an opportunity to be heard. Neither a jury trial nor proof beyond a reasonable doubt is required.<a href="http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/15/roger-shuler-convicted-of-resisting-arrest-remains-in-custody-for-contempt-of-prior-restraint-order/#wsa-endnote-2" name="wsa-inline-2"><sup>2</sup></a></p></blockquote>
<p>Shuler's contempt incarceration is nominally coercive rather than punitive &#8212; the Alabama court is putatively seeking to force him to comply with a (questionably lawful) order by imprisoning him until he obeys.  That doesn't mean it is without limits.  For instance, a court can't imprison you to coerce you do to something that's beyond your power.  As the <a href="http://law.justia.com/cases/alabama/supreme-court/1989/550-so-2d-1067-1.html" target="_blank">Supreme Court of Alabama said:</a></p>
<blockquote><p>Because incarceration on a finding of civil contempt is a sanction coercive in nature and is designed to compel compliance with the court's orders, when the punishment can no longer have any coercive effect it becomes punitive and may no longer be imposed. . . . Because it is impossible to coerce that which is beyond a person's power to perform, once the confinement ceases to have any coercive impact, continued imprisonment for civil contempt constitutes a violation of due process. </p></blockquote>
<p>Here, Shuler argued that he couldn't take down the blog posts from jail.  That might have been grounds to release him, had he not also apparently proclaimed in court that <a href="http://www.cbs42.com/news/hearing-on-blogger-injunction" target="_blank">he would not comply with the court's order</a>, rendering the inability moot.</p>
<p>So how long can he be kept in jail?  In that same decision quoted about, the Supreme Court of Alabama noted that someone subject to coercive contempt imprisonment "conceivably could have remained incarcerated indefinitely."  In many American jurisdictions that's correct &#8212; indefinite coercive incarceration is a tool that has led to <a href="http://www.dailynews.com/opinion/20100729/jayne-ressler-civil-contempt-confinement-policies-should-be-reformed" target="_blank">calls</a> for <a href="http://www.fee.org/the_freeman/detail/the-return-of-debtors-prison#axzz2qUrBR1r1" target="_blank">reform.</a>  In that Alabama case &#8212; which involved a mother refusing to disclose the location of a son suspected of arson &#8212; the Supreme Court of Alabama suggested that a court should revisit the issue:</p>
<blockquote><p>In cases such as this, after the contemnor has been incarcerated for a substantial length of time, the trial judge should bring the contemnor before him for another due process hearing in which he can reevaluate the factual basis of his first adjudication. If he is satisfied that his determination was correct, he should again incarcerate her. If he is of the opinion that she is telling the truth, of course, he should release her. </p></blockquote>
<p>Hopefully the Alabama court will revisit Shuler's incarceration.  At this point Shuler's options to get out of jail are to comply with the (probably unconstitutional) order or appeal it.  Given Shuler's behavior in court, I'm skeptical that he will be able to mount a successful appeal.  Telling the court <a href="http://www.cbs42.com/news/hearing-on-blogger-injunction" target="_blank">that it's a joke and (incorrectly) that it lacks jurisdiction over you</a> is generally not a recipe for appellate success.</p>
<p>We should be able to look critically both at Roger Shuler's behavior and of the system's treatment of him.  Notwithstanding overly credulous coverage (like <a href="http://www.salon.com/2014/01/14/jailing_of_an_alabama_blogger_its_worse_than_we_thought/" target="_blank">like Salon article that seems to accept Shuler's characterizations of his behavior uncritically and ignore the evidence of his actual behavior</a>), Shuler remains his own worst enemy.  His evasion of service, blogging about the same, and nutty-pro-se refusal to acknowledge the court all impede effective defense of his rights.  But even nuts and cranks deserve due process of law; depriving them of it threatens to weaken everyone's rights.  I'm troubled by how Shuler's civil and criminal cases were handled.  </p>
<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/15/roger-shuler-convicted-of-resisting-arrest-remains-in-custody-for-contempt-of-prior-restraint-order/">Roger Shuler Convicted of Resisting Arrest, Remains In Custody for Contempt of Prior Restraint Order</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
 <img src="http://www.popehat.com/?feed-stats-post-id=21341" width="1" height="1" style="display: none;" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/15/roger-shuler-convicted-of-resisting-arrest-remains-in-custody-for-contempt-of-prior-restraint-order/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>19</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/15/roger-shuler-convicted-of-resisting-arrest-remains-in-custody-for-contempt-of-prior-restraint-order/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>The Privilege To Shut Up</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Popehat/~3/VBcveYBgDm8/</link>
		<comments>http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/15/the-privilege-to-shut-up/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2014 16:17:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ken White]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics & Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cops]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Criminal Justice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Shut Up]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.popehat.com/?p=21336</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[One of the most consistent messages I offer here is about interactions with law enforcement, and can be expressed in two words &#8212; shut up &#8212; although "oh you dumb son of a bitch will you for the love of God shut up" might capture the flavor better. In brief, the reasons to shut up [&#8230;]<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/15/the-privilege-to-shut-up/">The Privilege To Shut Up</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One of the most consistent messages I offer here is about interactions with law enforcement, and can be expressed in two words &#8212; <a href="http://www.popehat.com/tag/shut-up/" target="_blank"><em>shut up</em></a> &#8212; although "oh you dumb son of a bitch will you for the love of God <em>shut up</em>" might capture the flavor better.  </p>
<p><span id="more-21336"></span></p>
<p>In brief, the reasons to shut up are these:  cops are not looking out for your best interests.  Cops are looking to make, or close, a case, which they seek to do according to their cultural preconceptions.  If you answer their questions, cops' evaluation of your words will be colored by their habitual assumption that you are lying.  That assumption may be premised on their culture, their <a href="http://tbo.com/list/columns-tjackson/jackson-gun-owner-unarmed-unwelcome-in-maryland-20140112/" target="_blank">simmering mood disorders,</a> their pathological tendency to associate <em>you</em> (whoever you are) with the very worst people they encounter on the job, and their evaluation of evidence they may or may not have understood.  If you talk to them, it is somewhere between possible and likely that you will incriminate yourself, whether or not you have done anything.  If you talk to them, it is possible that some types of cops will turn around and have you charged with a crime <a href="http://www.popehat.com/2013/05/01/shut-up-i-explained-mostly-pointlessly/" target="_blank">based on the talking itself</a>, upon a <a href="http://www.popehat.com/2011/12/01/reminder-oh-wont-you-please-shut-up/" target="_blank">thoroughly transparent theory</a> that you "obstructed" them.  Your instinct is to talk your way out of the situation, but that is an instinct born of prior interactions with reasonable people of good faith, and inapplicable to this interaction with people (1) who have mostly unchecked power over your and (2) who are, at the most optimistic, indifferent to how the interaction will turn out for you, and (3) who are perfectly capable of lying about what you said (or getting it wrong because they didn't understand it) and having their word <a href="http://www.popehat.com/2013/03/14/the-presumption-of-truth/" target="_blank">presumed true by the criminal justice system</a>.</p>
<p>So, I say, <em>don't talk to the cops.</em>  Ask to speak with an attorney, and get competent advice before you answer the cops' questions.  Are there mundane situations in which you might rationally decide to talk to the cops &#8212; say, if a neighbor's house is burglarized, and they come to ask if you saw anything?  Sure.  But you should view each interaction with the cops with an extreme caution bordering on paranoia, as you would handle a dangerous wild animal.  When you talk to a cop, you are talking to someone <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/national/officers-acquitted-in-death-of-kelly-thomas/2014/01/14/3e660b24-7d24-11e3-95c6-0a7aa80874bc_story.html" target="_blank">who is often privileged to kill you with complete impunity</a>, someone whose claims about what you said during your interaction &#8212; however fantastical &#8212; will likely be accepted uncritically by the system even if the particular cop is a <a href="http://www.popehat.com/2013/03/14/the-presumption-of-truth/" target="_blank">proven serial liar.</a>  Even the most mundane interaction carries the potential for life-altering disaster.</p>
<p>People ask commonly ask if this advice might lead police to suspect them of wrongdoing, or if it might even lead to their detention or arrest.  Yes, it might.  Life carries difficult choices and risk assessments.  One of those risk assessments is whether, in an interaction with police, it is more dangerous to talk, or more dangerous to shut up.  My point, in advocating shutting up, is to suggest that people's risk assessment is often misguided:  distorted by the cultural message that cops are the thin blue line of heroes we should trust, colored by our misplaced faith in our ability to talk our way out of situations, and incorrectly premised on the belief that cops asking questions will react fairly or in good faith to the answers.  People substantially <em>underestimate</em> the negative risks of interactions with law enforcement, and substantially <em>overestimate</em> the upside of such interactions.  Moreover, people underestimate not only the <em>amount</em> of risk of bad consequences, but the <em>extremity</em> of those consequences if they occur.  That's why I suggest that the risks of shutting up and asking to talk to a lawyer (which might include increased law enforcement suspicion of you, temporary detention, arrest, or even violence) are often outweighed by the downside risk of incriminating yourself or making a statement that cops will lie about or otherwise use against you.</p>
<p>Today I wanted to note that I recognize that my weighing of risks is colored by privilege.</p>
<p>"Privilege" is a term that's overused and misused in modern political discourse.  Too often it's used like a crass "shut up, I win" button in an argument.  But "privilege" is sometimes an apt descriptive term of a human phenomenon:  a person's evaluation of a situation (like interaction with law enforcement) is colored by his or her own experiences, and those experiences are usually circumscribed by that person's cultural identity and wealth.  Any criminal defense attorney who has served affluent clients is familiar with this:  such clients often conclude that they are a victim of a conspiracy, or of a "rogue cop" or "loose cannon prosecutor," because their life experiences lead them to assume that the system <em>can't possibly</em> treat all people the way they are being treated.  By contrast, clients who have lived in poverty (or clients who are African-American or Latino) tend to recognize outrageous conduct in their case as the system working the way the system typically works &#8212; <em>business as usual.</em>  In my <a href="http://www.popehat.com/2013/03/24/three-things-you-may-not-get-about-the-aaron-swartz-case/" target="_blank">post about the prosecution and death of Aaron Swartz,</a> I argued that Swartz' community showed such privilege in its reaction to his prosecution, seeing some sort of singular conspiracy where others saw the banal grinding of the system's unfeeling wheels.      </p>
<p>My advice to shut up is colored, in part, by privilege.  I was reminded of this yesterday <a href="http://www.cnn.com/2014/01/14/showbiz/ent-justin-bieber-vandalism-probe/" target="_blank">when Los Angeles County Sheriff's Deputies searched Justin Bieber's house</a>.  I praised Bieber for shutting up and declining to talk to the cops, and joked that criminal defense attorneys could shame clients into better practices by asking why they aren't smarter than Justin Bieber.</p>
<p>But Justin Bieber and I &#8212; and many of my clients &#8212; share a crucial quality:  we're affluent and fortunate.  This privilege makes us better able to endure the potential downside risks of shutting up.  If we get arrested on a petty or bogus charge by a pissed-off cop, we can make bail.  We won't spend weeks or months in custody on that bogus charge because we can't scrape together a few thousand dollars.  Maybe we'll spend the weekend in jail, because cops love to arrest you Friday afternoon, but we'll get out in a few days at most, and in the meantime we won't lose our jobs.  Because we have families and support systems, if we do get thrown in jail on a bogus job by an angry cop, the Department of Child and Family Services won't take away our children, plunging us into <em>another</em> broken system we have neither the money nor the knowledge to navigate.  If the cops tow or impound our car, we can afford to pay the few hundred to few thousand dollars to get it out, and we won't lose our jobs for lack of transportation.  Even if we do lose our jobs because of a bogus and retaliatory arrest, we have savings, and families with savings, and we won't swiftly lose our homes.  If the police choose to retaliate against our silence with petty tickets and infractions and fines rather than arrest, we can fight them or absorb them.  </p>
<p>That's a privilege.  Poor people don't have it.  Poor people live on the razor's edge, and a bogus retaliatory arrest can destroy them.  <a href="http://reason.com/archives/2014/01/08/petty-law-enforcement-vs-the-poor" target="_blank">Retaliatory and capricious enforcement of petty crimes and infractions can destroy them financially.</a>  Police wield disproportionate power over them, and the criminal justice system and its agendas (like the <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/erikkain/2011/06/28/the-war-on-drugs-is-a-war-on-minorities-and-the-poor/" target="_blank">War on Drugs</a>) disproportionately impacts them.  Police are more likely to <a href="https://www.ncjrs.gov/App/publications/abstract.aspx?ID=201571" target="_blank">use force against poor people</a> and for the most part <a href="http://www.texasobserver.org/horror-every-day-police-brutality-houston-goes-unpunished/" target="_blank">can do so without any significant risk of discipline.</a>      </p>
<p>When you and I weigh the downside risks of shutting up against the downside risks of talking, our downside risks are milder, and can be endured.  People without our resources face a must starker choice:  talk, and incriminate themselves, or shut up, and face an array of consequences they may not be equipped to survive.    </p>
<p>I maintain my advice to shut up.  But I acknowledge it's easier and safer for me &#8212; and for most of the people reading this blog &#8212; than it is for the people who most frequently encounter the police.       </p>
<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/15/the-privilege-to-shut-up/">The Privilege To Shut Up</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
 <img src="http://www.popehat.com/?feed-stats-post-id=21336" width="1" height="1" style="display: none;" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/15/the-privilege-to-shut-up/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>74</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/15/the-privilege-to-shut-up/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>A Funny Joke</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Popehat/~3/lbaijuPwPm0/</link>
		<comments>http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/09/a-funny-joke/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2014 14:51:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Clark]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effluvia]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.popehat.com/?p=21329</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[You know what would be a funny joke? When you catch a guy driving drunk, instead of giving him a breathalizer test and then taking him to jail, instead zip tie his hands and then leave him in a Taco Bell parking lot. &#8230;because he's Mexican, get it? What's that? The drunk guy wandered into [&#8230;]<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/09/a-funny-joke/">A Funny Joke</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>You know what would be a funny joke?</p>
<p>When you catch a guy driving drunk, instead of giving him a breathalizer test and then taking him to jail, instead zip tie his hands and then leave him in a Taco Bell parking lot.</p>
<p>&#8230;because he's <i>Mexican</i>, get it?</p>
<p>What's that?</p>
<p>The drunk guy wandered into traffic, hands behind his back, and got <a href="http://www.courthousenews.com/2014/01/09/64369.htm">struck and killed by a car</a>?</p>
<p>Uh &#8211; no comment.</p>
<p>Talk to our union lawyer.</p>
<p>And put down that camera, mother-fucker!</p>
<p>&lt; pulls on rubber gloves &gt;</p>
<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/09/a-funny-joke/">A Funny Joke</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
 <img src="http://www.popehat.com/?feed-stats-post-id=21329" width="1" height="1" style="display: none;" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/09/a-funny-joke/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>67</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/09/a-funny-joke/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Alex Marthews Sees the Police State Being Forged and Does Not Like It</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Popehat/~3/VTvIhmCgRSg/</link>
		<comments>http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/08/alex-marthews-sees-the-police-state-being-forged-and-does-not-like-it/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2014 15:40:24 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Clark]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effluvia]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.popehat.com/?p=21324</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This essay ( Quit Throwing 9/11 In Our Faces ) is quite something. Like me, Alex Marthews prefers not to drop the f-bomb &#8230;but there are times that try men's souls, and our ongoing slide into an actual honest-to-God yes-it-can-happen-here police state is one of them, and it's pushed both of us into it recently. [&#8230;]<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/08/alex-marthews-sees-the-police-state-being-forged-and-does-not-like-it/">Alex Marthews Sees the Police State Being Forged and Does Not Like It</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This essay ( <a href="http://warrantless.org/2014/01/no-more-911/">Quit Throwing 9/11 In Our Faces</a> ) is quite something.  </p>
<p>Like me, Alex Marthews prefers not to drop the f-bomb &#8230;but there are times that try men's souls, and our ongoing slide into an actual honest-to-God yes-it-can-happen-here police state is one of them, and it's pushed both of us into it recently.</p>
<p>What's got Alex's blood up today?<br />
<span id="more-21324"></span><br />
The facts that</p>
<p>(a) the NSA had all the intel it needed to prevent 9/11, as revealed in this open letter to the president from "Former NSA Senior Executives/Veteran Intelligence Professionals for Sanity (VIPS)",</p>
<blockquote>
<p>	The sadder reality, Mr. President, is that NSA itself had enough information to prevent 9/11, but chose to sit on it rather than share it with the FBI or CIA. We know; we were there. We were witness to the many bureaucratic indignities that made NSA at least as culpable for pre-9/11 failures as are other U.S. intelligence agencies.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>and </p>
<p>(b) in response to its failure, the NSA and other intelligence agencies have not done honest soul-searching but have instead engaged in coverups and a concerted push to increase the collection of data on US citizens, even though they have no ability to deal with that data and there is no argument that this increased domestic spying will help protect the people.</p>
<p>Here's Alex's rage money-shot, and as a fellow defender of liberty who &#8211; more and more &#8211; alternates between near tears and near screaming over how the corpse of our Republic is being raped, I applaud it:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>	I am fucking pissed off. What a fuckup. What a gargantuan, despicable, offensive fuckup.</p>
<p>	These clowns gleefully threw the Constitution on the fire, and gave us NOTHING in return. We’re not safer. We’re certainly not richer. We have lost so much, so that a few people could become extremely rich and powerful, and our corrupt system is now incapable of holding them personally to account. Yet still they yammer on, clamoring for more funding for an NSA that doesn’t work, a TSA that doesn’t work, an FBI that chases imaginary plots instead of focusing on locking up actual criminals. They have played on our fears to make us exchange realistic risk assessment for a meaningless, nightmarish pantomime where we, the American people and indeed the people of the whole world, have to accept the loss of every freedom we hold dear in order to “do whatever it takes” to “catch the bad guys.”</p>
<p>	I’m sick of it. Aren’t you sick of it? I am goddamn heart-sick of it.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I really hate to use the phrase "police state" (as I did above), because it makes one sound like a silly 19 year old who is upset that mom and dad wouldn't let him borrow the station wagon to get to the mall, and furthermore that when he got to the mall anyway, the fascist thugs at the CD store kept following him around as if he was a shoplifter.</p>
<p>The thing is,  though, we <i>are</i> drifting into a police state.  Or, rather, we've already crossed the boundary and we're drifting deeper and deeper into the funnel.  This is a tragedy that's hard to explain (or, at least, requires more skill than I have at my command this morning).  There's<br />
<a href="http://www.econlib.org/library/YPDBooks/Rae/raeLS22.html">a great deal of ruin in a nation</a>, Adam Smith once famously said, but when we're spending $52.6 billion per year in<br />
<a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/national-security/black-budget-summary-details-us-spy-networks-successes-failures-and-objectives/2013/08/29/7e57bb78-10ab-11e3-8cdd-bcdc09410972_story.html">the black budget</a> (that's $100,000 per minute) to wiretap on the citizenry, develop zero day exploits to give the government the ability to take over our infrastructure, launch spy satellites, and more, the a huge amount of ruin can happen at a speed far faster than Adam Smith ever imagined.</p>
<p>Again, I apologize for what sounds like melodrama, but we are destroying our Republic and our individual freedoms at an astounding rate.  Like clear cutting and burning rain-forests, we are reducing to ash in years and months a tradition that took centuries to build.</p>
<p>It's far far easier to destroy a culture than it is to bring it back.  Cultures, like rain-forests and cathedrals, grow slowly, and take centuries to mature and ripen&#8230;and yet can be smashed in a historical eye-blink.  The problem isn't merely that the government is spying <i>today</i>; the problem is that we are teaching ourselves, our bureaucrats &#8211; and worst of all, our children &#8211; that this is acceptable, that the people exist to serve the State, that a prudent government keeps track of all of its citizens in the same way that a prudent farmer puts ear-tags on all of his cattle.</p>
<p>Go read Alex's <a href="http://warrantless.org/2014/01/no-more-911/">masterful rant</a> and make sure to read<br />
<a href="http://consortiumnews.com/2014/01/07/nsa-insiders-reveal-what-went-wrong/">the whistle-blowing letter</a> that set him off.</p>
<p>Most days I frankly don't think it's possible to stop our slide into soft (if we're lucky) fascism.  Today is one of those days&#8230;.or maybe, just maybe it's not.  I've got just a touch of optimism in my soul this morning.</p>
<p>Either way, we've got to try to prevent the police state from solidifying its grip, damn it.  </p>
<p>No matter what, blood is going to be spilled, money is going to be wasted, and rights are going to be violated.</p>
<p>&#8230;but if we fight now, the blood will be that of a few hundred peaceful protesters cheerfully allowing themselves to be clubbed by riot police, the money that is going to be wasted is going to be kickstarted legal defense funds, and the rights are going to be those of modern-day Rosa Parks who allow themselves to be arrested so that the populace is confronted with the brutality of the system.</p>
<p>If we don't fight now, though, the national-security-police-state will win, and it will be our children, or our children's children, who will have to fight.  And their fight might look a lot less like the American Civil Rights movement and a lot more like some goddamned bloody unwinable mess like the Syrian Civil War, or the horrific Khmer Rouge paroxysms.</p>
<p>My next post should be "How Do We Fight?"</p>
<p>The problem is, I don't know.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/08/alex-marthews-sees-the-police-state-being-forged-and-does-not-like-it/">Alex Marthews Sees the Police State Being Forged and Does Not Like It</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
 <img src="http://www.popehat.com/?feed-stats-post-id=21324" width="1" height="1" style="display: none;" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/08/alex-marthews-sees-the-police-state-being-forged-and-does-not-like-it/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>87</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/08/alex-marthews-sees-the-police-state-being-forged-and-does-not-like-it/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>An Anarcho Capitalist Camel Nose Under the Tent Disguised as a Modest Wonkish Proposal</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Popehat/~3/kDLznepmlxE/</link>
		<comments>http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/06/an-anarcho-capitalist-camel-nose-under-the-tent-disguised-as-a-modest-wonkish-proposal/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2014 21:43:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Clark]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effluvia]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.popehat.com/?p=21322</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In a better world, cops would have to buy malpractice insurance. Dangerous cops would have to pay more, leading some to change careers. &#8212; ClarkHat (@ClarkHat) January 6, 2014 An Anarcho Capitalist Camel Nose Under the Tent Disguised as a Modest Wonkish Proposal © 2007-2013 by the authors of Popehat. This feed is for personal, [&#8230;]<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/06/an-anarcho-capitalist-camel-nose-under-the-tent-disguised-as-a-modest-wonkish-proposal/">An Anarcho Capitalist Camel Nose Under the Tent Disguised as a Modest Wonkish Proposal</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" width="500"><p>In a better world, cops would have to buy malpractice insurance.  Dangerous cops would have to pay more, leading some to change careers.</p>
<p>&mdash; ClarkHat (@ClarkHat) <a href="https://twitter.com/ClarkHat/statuses/420254393444093952">January 6, 2014</a></p></blockquote>
<p><script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/06/an-anarcho-capitalist-camel-nose-under-the-tent-disguised-as-a-modest-wonkish-proposal/">An Anarcho Capitalist Camel Nose Under the Tent Disguised as a Modest Wonkish Proposal</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
 <img src="http://www.popehat.com/?feed-stats-post-id=21322" width="1" height="1" style="display: none;" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/06/an-anarcho-capitalist-camel-nose-under-the-tent-disguised-as-a-modest-wonkish-proposal/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>89</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/06/an-anarcho-capitalist-camel-nose-under-the-tent-disguised-as-a-modest-wonkish-proposal/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Fear And Loathing In Falls Church</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Popehat/~3/UlcqwHqQUOw/</link>
		<comments>http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/04/fear-and-loathing-in-falls-church/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2014 16:14:29 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Patrick Non-White]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Irksome]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[David Brooks]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.popehat.com/?p=21311</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[CHAPTER ONE The silver 2001 BMW 535i roared through Adams Morgan, occasionally screeching over the sidewalks as my accountant wrenched both hands from the wheel for another toke at the weed-pipe. "Gadzooks, man!" I shouted. "Can you keep it together for another fifteen miles, or at least outside the District limits?"  We were halfway through [&#8230;]<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/04/fear-and-loathing-in-falls-church/">Fear And Loathing In Falls Church</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>CHAPTER ONE</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/04/fear-and-loathing-in-falls-church/david-brooks/" rel="attachment wp-att-21313"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-21313" alt="David Brooks" src="http://www.popehat.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/David-Brooks.jpg" width="350" height="450" /></a></p>
<p>The silver 2001 BMW 535i roared through Adams Morgan, occasionally screeching over the sidewalks as my accountant wrenched both hands from the wheel for <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/01/03/opinion/brooks-weed-been-there-done-that.html" target="_blank">another toke at the weed-pipe.</a> "Gadzooks, man!" I shouted. "Can you keep it together for another fifteen miles, or at least outside the District limits?"  We were halfway through our 35 mile journey from Bethesda to Falls Church, with enough dangerous narcotics to stun a grizzly bear in the trunk: We'd started with nine ounces of weed, six rocks of crack, a sugar jar full of blow,  36 vicodin tablets,  a cage filled with live Bolivian arrow toads, and two jars of ketamine. Plus two quarts of Beefeater gin, a case of Schlitz malt liquor, and a four ounce ball of Afghan hash: Surely enough to get this pair of degenerate drug addicts to Fall's Church. After that what man could say?</p>
<p>It was Edmund Burke, the English statesman and philosopher of the Good Life, who asked, "What is liberty without wisdom and without virtue?" In the Burkean <em>ethos</em>, freedom unconstrained by wisdom "is the greatest of all possible evils; for it is folly, vice, and madness, without tuition or restraint." I reflected that Burke's wisdom had never been constrained by a head full of mescaline, or a heart thumping on two tabs of amyl nitrate, so perhaps there were things the grand old man of the eighteenth century British <em>polity</em> did not know.</p>
<p>"Keep your God-damned mitts on the wheel!" I shouted at my accountant as the BMW lurched off of the sidewalk, narrowly missing a parking enforcement officer who stood gaping in confusion at my accountant's attempt to achieve manned space flight using only the power of internal combustion and a brain tripping on liquid sunshine. "Do you want to get us busted?" There was madness in his eyes, but I couldn't help looking at his <a href="http://minx.cc/?post=291599" target="_blank">pant leg and his perfectly creased pant.</a> And I was thinking, a) he got into the ketamine before we left Bethesda and b) we'll be staying overnight at the DC Correctional Treatment Facility for Narcotics Addicts. I put those thoughts out of my head, distracted by the mescaline-induced vision of my accountant vomiting up, one by one, the collected works of British conservative <a href="http://justoneminute.typepad.com/main/2013/12/david-brooks-versus-the-thought-leaders.html" target="_blank">thought leader</a> Michael Oakeshott, all bound in the finest red leather.</p>
<p>Oakeshott famously said that as civilized human beings, we are the inheritors, neither of an inquiry about ourselves and the world, nor of an accumulating body of information, but of a conversation, begun in the primeval forests and extended and made more articulate in the course of centuries. It is a conversation which goes on both in public and within each of ourselves. I believe that if our national political conversation were better informed by the spirit of Oakeshott, and less by the spirit of <em>Manichaeism</em>, ours would be a happier society.</p>
<p>But ours was not a happier society. This was fascist (or more correctly, <em>corporatist</em>) George W. Bush's America. Two years after the dawn of the new millennium Jesus was nowhere in sight, because the Feds were cracking down like sledgehammers on the ecstasy dealers. As senior political editor for the Weekly Standard, I had been sent to cover Bill Bennett's address on education policy at the annual convention of the Young Americans for Freedom. I was here to cover the story! And cover it I would, fueled by the finest mind altering products that 21st century biochemistry had to offer.</p>
<p>As we hit the Virginia line, I mused on the fine line that exists between a state of ordered liberty, in which government serves the needs of the majority, gently nudging the masses toward the higher pleasures, and the state of shocking, bestial depravity that was the passenger compartment of my accountant's BMW: open liquor bottles, a rear windshield plastered with pictures cut from the pages of <em>Hustler</em> and <em>Love Bondage Fantasy!</em> magazines, and in the vomit-drenched back seat, Kareem, a crack dealer we'd picked up in Anacostia, vainly trying to sleep off last night's festivities as the BMW careened from lane to lane like some cocaine-propelled mule train that never existed except in <a href="http://www.popehat.com/2009/05/08/republicans-the-party-of-anarchy/" target="_blank">John Ford's wildest dreams.</a></p>
<p>"Kids today just can't handle their drugs," my accountant muttered through the shroud of opium that fogged his brain. "WHAT?!?" I shouted, cutting down the volume on the "Enter the Wu-Tang (36 Chambers)" compact disc my accountant had fished out of Kareem's backpack. And that's when it hit me, like an electro-plated dung truck: We were not living in John Ford's America. You see, the greatest of all Western directors, John Ford, actually used Westerns to tell a story not of rugged individualism, but to celebrate the notion of civic order. At his finest, Ford teaches us all about the concrete ways people build orderly neighborhoods, and how those neighborhoods bind together to form a nation. The West of Ford is a lawless  and disordered place, requiring the prepoplitical virtues of a man who possesses the willingness to seek revenge, to mete out justice on his own. That kind of person hardly makes for an ordered polity. But, as this sort of classic western hero tames the West, he makes himself obsolete. Once the western towns have been pacified, there’s no need for his capacity for violence, nor for his righteous justice. As New York University film critic Sander Starr has pointed out, in the individual are planted the seeds of his own destruction. Only through the mediating agency of the panopticon state can this tendency toward self-destruction be averted and channeled into socially productive uses.</p>
<p>"That's some super-heavy shit," I croaked, seizing the weed-pipe from my accountant's lap. "How many miles til Falls Church?"</p>
<p>"We passed it five hours ago. We'll be pulling into Virginia Beach any minute now. Should be lotsa hookers in town this time of year. It's Bike Week."</p>
<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/04/fear-and-loathing-in-falls-church/">Fear And Loathing In Falls Church</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
 <img src="http://www.popehat.com/?feed-stats-post-id=21311" width="1" height="1" style="display: none;" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/04/fear-and-loathing-in-falls-church/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>42</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://www.popehat.com/2014/01/04/fear-and-loathing-in-falls-church/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Also, The Pony Will Need Three References</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Popehat/~3/WzifObm5b_8/</link>
		<comments>http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/31/also-the-pony-will-need-three-references/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2013 18:43:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ken White]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Fun]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Humor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marketing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spammers]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.popehat.com/?p=21306</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Hi Ken, I’m Rebecca Gray from Backgroundchecks.org. I love writing guest posts for blogs that interest me. It's a great way to expand one's portfolio, network with other bloggers, and learn new things. That being said, I was wondering if I could write a guest post for you. The article will be unique and specifically [&#8230;]<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/31/also-the-pony-will-need-three-references/">Also, The Pony Will Need Three References</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Hi Ken,</p>
<p>I’m Rebecca Gray from Backgroundchecks.org. I love writing guest posts for blogs that interest me. It's a great way to expand one's portfolio, network with other bloggers, and learn new things.</p>
<p>That being said, I was wondering if I could write a guest post for you. The article will be unique and specifically tailored as per the theme of your blog. I’ll just include a reference to my site in the author byline at the end of the article.</p>
<p>Please let me know if you are interested.</p>
<p>Thanks,<br />
Rebecca</p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Dear Rebecca,</p>
<p>Happy New Year!  I'm pleased that we can provide an opportunity to expand someone's portfolio.</p>
<p>We're excited to hear that you can offer specifically tailored guest posts per the theme of our blog.  Most people don't get the theme of our blog quite frankly. </p>
<p>So:  I see you are from Backgroundchecks.org.  Can you provide a specifically tailored guest post about background checks?  If so I have a few specifications and questions for such a post.</p>
<p>Ken<br />
www.popehat.com</p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Hi Ken,</p>
<p>Thanks for the response. Well, I would love to write an article related to background checks. Please let me know if you have any specific topic in mind.</p>
<p>Best,<br />
Rebecca</p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Rebecca:</p>
<p>Well, here's the thing.  Most available articles about background checks involve people.</p>
<p>Now I grant you that in many ways this is sensible.  Man, we are told, is the most dangerous game.  Also not an island, and the bastard, and to the extent he is good, hard to find.  Man is also a battlefield, if I recall correctly.</p>
<p>But what about other threats?</p>
<p>Is it possible to run a background check on a pony?</p>
<p>Now, wait.  I recognize you will see this as immediately preposterous.  "What kind of idiot has to run a background check on a pony," you might be thinking.  "A pony is overtly hazardous, a patent threat by definition.  You might as well run a background check on a puddle of acid or a board with a rusty nail or R. Kelly."</p>
<p>But there are gradations of risk, Rebecca.  We deal with them every day.  Do I speed up to make that yellow light, or slow down?  Do I try skydiving, or not?  Do I eat another Double-Double animal style from In-N-Out Burger even though my entire abdomen is so taut and bloated that my vision is blurred and I can feel my pulse in my scrotum?</p>
<p>All ponies are wicked and hazardous, but surely some ponies are more deadly than others.  For instance, though all ponies would bite our precious children given a suitable opportunity, some have actually done so and developed a taste for man-flesh that torments their dreams and makes them shudder when darling little hands run over their manes.  Any pony MIGHT kill a man, but some ponies HAVE killed a man, and have begun to develop . . . . skills.  It's like the difference between a job applicant who has a proven record of being repeatedly fired for incompetence, and one who merely has visible barbed wire or tribal tattoos.</p>
<p>So:  I guess what I'm looking for is an article on the extent to which modern technology and investigative methods has made it practicable to run background checks on ponies before one retains their services for one purpose or another.</p>
<p>Also:  our readers have grown extremely wary to the point of unmedicated phobia about ponies.  So the article should be ABOUT ponies but under no circumstances should the article SAY "pony" or directly mention anything clearly pony-related like "hoof" or "snort" or "rend."  Kindly employ a euphemism instead, viz. "In this article I will discuss whether it is possible to run a background check on William Howard Taft, 27th President of the United States of America, in order to protect your children."</p>
<p>Trusting that these terms will be agreeable, I remain very sincerely yours,</p>
<p>Ken<br />
www.popehat.com</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/31/also-the-pony-will-need-three-references/">Also, The Pony Will Need Three References</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
 <img src="http://www.popehat.com/?feed-stats-post-id=21306" width="1" height="1" style="display: none;" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/31/also-the-pony-will-need-three-references/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>78</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/31/also-the-pony-will-need-three-references/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Would You Buy a Used Macroeconomic Policy From This Man?</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Popehat/~3/KjkPIk3Ou1s/</link>
		<comments>http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/29/would-you-buy-a-used-macroeconomic-policy-from-this-man/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2013 19:13:29 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Clark]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effluvia]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.popehat.com/?p=21297</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[(source) Would You Buy a Used Macroeconomic Policy From This Man? © 2007-2013 by the authors of Popehat. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/29/would-you-buy-a-used-macroeconomic-policy-from-this-man/">Would You Buy a Used Macroeconomic Policy From This Man?</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img border=0 src="http://www.popehat.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/krugman.png" style="float:left; margin:10px; width:400px;"/></p>
<div style="clear:both;"></div>
<p>(<a href="http://web.archive.org/web/19980610100009/www.redherring.com/mag/issue55/economics.html">source</a>)</p>
<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/29/would-you-buy-a-used-macroeconomic-policy-from-this-man/">Would You Buy a Used Macroeconomic Policy From This Man?</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
 <img src="http://www.popehat.com/?feed-stats-post-id=21297" width="1" height="1" style="display: none;" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/29/would-you-buy-a-used-macroeconomic-policy-from-this-man/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>194</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/29/would-you-buy-a-used-macroeconomic-policy-from-this-man/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Pyramid Song</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Popehat/~3/bBjcgsysaxg/</link>
		<comments>http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/27/pyramid-song/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2013 00:49:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[David]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[music]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.popehat.com/?p=21288</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Radiohead, Pyramid Song, covered by Sybarite5 in an arrangement by Paul Kim. See also, especially if you know the original well, their version of Packt Like Sardines in a Crushd Tin Box. Pyramid Song © 2007-2013 by the authors of Popehat. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other [&#8230;]<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/27/pyramid-song/">Pyramid Song</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span class='embed-youtube' style='text-align:center; display: block;'><iframe class='youtube-player' type='text/html' width='480' height='300' src='http://www.youtube.com/embed/wenjdtY-qaE?version=3&#038;rel=1&#038;fs=1&#038;showsearch=0&#038;showinfo=1&#038;iv_load_policy=1&#038;wmode=transparent' frameborder='0'></iframe></span></p>
<p>Radiohead, <a title="Radiohead, Pyramid Song" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=s2VzLn6DMCE" target="_blank"><em>Pyramid Song</em></a>, covered by <a title="Sybarite 5" href="www.sybarite5.org" target="_blank">Sybarite5</a> in an arrangement by Paul Kim.</p>
<p>See also, especially if you know <a title="Radiohead, Packt Like Sardines in a Crushd Tin Box" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RU8slEG-OtM" target="_blank">the original</a> well, their version of <a title="Sybarite5 covering Packt Like Sardines" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iTeXWv__Dwc" target="_blank"><em>Packt Like Sardines in a Crushd Tin Box</em></a>.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/27/pyramid-song/">Pyramid Song</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
 <img src="http://www.popehat.com/?feed-stats-post-id=21288" width="1" height="1" style="display: none;" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/27/pyramid-song/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>5</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/27/pyramid-song/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Merry Christmas!</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Popehat/~3/kWBuweASMag/</link>
		<comments>http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/24/decrying-constancys-loss-in-change/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2013 05:45:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[David]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Poetry]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.popehat.com/?p=21274</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[A Christmas Prayer Decrying constancy's loss in change, When winter reigns, bestow a benediction. Each heavenly tear its mate in ink arrange And color the frigid winter with other diction, Denying even the season's wonted selection Of font and fiction. Palette in lip, hand, eye, Teach me to meet with reason each objection, The winter [&#8230;]<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/24/decrying-constancys-loss-in-change/">Merry Christmas!</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="padding-left: 120px;">A Christmas Prayer</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px;">Decrying constancy's loss in change,<br />
When winter reigns, bestow a benediction.<br />
Each heavenly tear its mate in ink arrange<br />
And color the frigid winter with other diction,<br />
Denying even the season's wonted selection<br />
Of font and fiction. Palette in lip, hand, eye,<br />
Teach me to meet with reason each objection,<br />
The winter rains. Take aim and touch the sky,<br />
Thy brush whispering whether and winter and why,<br />
Chromatically ascribing. Let the distraction<br />
Of days too short to long&#8211; their periphery<br />
Restriction, their center dramatic reaction&#8211;<br />
Be painted with memories of a day preferred,<br />
And given essence by Thy blessed Word.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 150px;">~David Byron for Cathie<br />
in the winter of 1991.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/24/decrying-constancys-loss-in-change/">Merry Christmas!</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
 <img src="http://www.popehat.com/?feed-stats-post-id=21274" width="1" height="1" style="display: none;" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/24/decrying-constancys-loss-in-change/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>7</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/24/decrying-constancys-loss-in-change/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Burn the Fucking System to the Ground</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Popehat/~3/arebI2GWzUc/</link>
		<comments>http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/23/burn-the-fucking-system-to-the-ground/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2013 03:29:31 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Clark]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effluvia]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.popehat.com/?p=21266</guid>
		<description><![CDATA["I'm a good judge" &#8230; said by government employee and judge Gisele Pollack who, it seems, sentenced people to jail because of their drug use&#8230;while she, herself, was high on drugs. But, in her defense, "she’s had some severe personal tragedy in her life". And that's why, it seems, she's being allowed to check herself [&#8230;]<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/23/burn-the-fucking-system-to-the-ground/">Burn the Fucking System to the Ground</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>"I'm a good judge" &#8230; said by government employee and judge Gisele Pollack who, it seems, sentenced people to jail because of their drug use&#8230;<a href="http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2528407/Drug-court-judge-enters-rehab-court-meltdown.html">while she, herself, was high on drugs</a>.</p>
<p>But, in her defense, "she’s had some severe personal tragedy in her life".</p>
<p>And that's why, it seems, she's being allowed to check herself into rehab instead of being thrown in jail.</p>
<p><span id="more-21266"></span></p>
<p>&#8230;because not a single poor person or non government employee who gets caught using drugs ever "had some severe personal tragedy in her life".</p>
<p>I'm reminded of something I read earlier today:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><a href="http://www.techdirt.com/articles/20131222/00342325665/govt-ignores-cia-boss-leaking-classified-bin-laden-raid-info-instead-pursues-leaker-report-blaming-him.shtml">techdirt.com</a></p>
<p>	We've discussed the whole "high court/low court" concept here a few times before &#8212; in that those who are powerful play by one set of rules, while the rest of us have to play by a very different set of rules.</p>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<p>The end result seems clear. If you're super high up in the political chain, you get the high court. Reveal classified info to filmmakers? No worries. Not only will you not be prosecuted or even lose your job, the inspectors will scrub your name from the report and, according to the article, the person in charge of the investigation will "slow roll" the eventual release of the report until you switch jobs. </p>
<p>But if you're just a worker bee and you leaked the unclassified draft report that names Panetta and Vickers? Well, you get the low court. A new investigation, including aggressive pursuit by the government, and interrogations of staffers to try to find out who leaked the report.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Twenty years ago I was a libertarian.  I thought the system could be reformed.  I thought that <i>some</i> parts of it "worked"&#8230; whatever that means.  I thought that the goals were noble, even if not often achieved.</p>
<p>The older I get, the more I see, the more I read, the more clear it becomes to me that the entire game is rigged.  The leftists and the rightists each see half of the fraud.  The lefties correctly note that a poor kid caught with cocaine goes to jail, while a Bush can write it off as a youthful mistake (they somehow overlook the fact that their man Barrack hasn't granted clemency to any one of the people doing federal time for the same felonies he committed).  The righties note that government subsidized windmills kill protected eagles with impunity while Joe Sixpack would be deep in the crap if he even picked up a dead eagle from the side of the road.  The lefties note that no one was prosecuted over the financial meltdown.  The righties note that the Obama administration rewrote bankruptcy law on the fly to loot value from GM stockholders and hand it to the unions.  The lefties note that Republicans tweak export rules to give big corporations subsidies.  Every now and then both sides join together to note that, hey! the government is spying on every one of us&#8230;or that, hey! the government stole a bunch of people's houses and gave them to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kelo_v._City_of_New_London">Pfizer</a>, because a privately owned for-profit corporation is apparently what the Constitution means by "public use".</p>
<p>What neither side seems to realize is that the system is not reformable.  There are multiple classes of people, but it boils down to the connected, and the not connected.  Just as in pre-Revolutionary France, there is a very strict class hierarchy, and the very idea that we are equal before the law is a laughable nonsequitr.</p>
<p>Jamal the $5 weed slinger, Shaneekwa the hair braider, and Loudmouth Bob in the 7-11 parking lot are at the bottom of the hierarchy.  They can, <i>literally</i>, be killed with impunity &#8230; as long as the dash cam isn't running.  And, hell, half the time they can be killed even if the dash cam <i>is</i> running.  This isn't hyperbole, mother-fucker.  This is <i>literal</i>.  Question me and I'll throw 400 cites and 20 youtube clips at you.</p>
<p>Next up from Shaneekwa and Loudmouth Bob are us regular peons.  We can have our balls squeezed at the airport, our rectums explored at the roadside, our cars searched because the cops got permission from a dog (I owe some Reason intern a drink for that one), our telephones tapped (because terrorism!), our bank accounts investigated (because FinCEN! and no expectation of privacy!).  We don't own the house we live in, not if someone of a higher social class wants it.  We don't own our own financial lives, because the <s>education</s> accreditation / student loan industry / legal triumvirate have declared that we can never escape &#8211; even through bankruptcy &#8211; our $200,000 debt that a bunch of adults convinced a can't-tell-his-ass-from-a-hole-in-the-ground 18 year old that (a) he was smart enough to make his own decisions, and (b) college is a time to explore your interests and broaden yourself).  And if there's a "national security emergency" (defined as two idiots with a pressure cooker), then the constitution is suspended, martial law is declared, and people are hauled out of their homes.</p>
<p>Next up from the regular peons are the unionized, disciplined-voting-blocks.  Not-much-brighter-than-a-box-of-crayolas teachers who work 180 days a year and get automatic raises.  Firefighters who disproportionately retire on disability the very day they sub in for their bosses and get a paper cut.</p>
<p>A step up from the teachers and firefighters are the cops: all the same advantages of nobility of the previous group, but a few more in addition: the de facto power to murder someone as long as not <i>too</i> many cameras are rolling.  The de facto power to confiscate cameras in case the murder wasn't well planned.  A right to keep and bear arms that far exceeds that of the serf class: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Law_Enforcement_Officers_Safety_Act">50 state concealed carry for life</a>, not just just for actual cops, but even for <i>retired</i> cops.</p>
<p>At the same level of privilege as cops, but slightly off to one side is different class of nobility: the judiciary and the prosecutors.  Judges and prosecutors can't execute citizens in an alley, a parking lot, or their own homes ("he had a knife! &#8230;and I don't care what the lying video says."), but they can sentence people to decades in jail for things that any clear-minded reading of the Constitution and the 9th and 10th amendments make clear are not with in the purview of the government.  They have effectively infinite resources.  They orchestrate perp walks.  They selectively leak information to shame defendants.  They buy testimony from other defendants by promising them immunity.  By exercising their discretion they make sure that the bad people are prosecuted while the good people (i.e. members of their own clan) are not.</p>
<p>Above the cops, the prosecutors, and the judiciary we have the true ruling class: the cabal of (most) politicians and (some) CEOs, conspiring both against their own competitors and the public at large.  If the public is burdened with a $100 million debt to pay off a money losing stadium, that's a small price to pay if a politician gets reelected (and gets to hobnob with entertainers and sports heroes via free tickets and backstage passes).  If new entrants into a market are hindered and the populace ends up overpaying for coffins, or Tesla cars, or wine that can't be mail ordered, then that's a small price to pay if a connected CEO can keep his firm profitable without doing any work to help the customer.  If the Google founders want to agitate for Green laws that make Joe Sixpack's daily commute more expensive at the same time that they buy <a href="http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/12/12/google-executives-got-discounts-from-government-on-fuel-for-private-aircraft/?_r=0">discount avgas</a> for their <a href="http://searchenginewatch.com/article/2058308/Lawsuits-Over-The-Google-Party-Jet-Arguments-Over-Bed-Sizes-On-Board">private flying fuck palaces</a>, then isn't that their right?  They donated to Obama's campaign after all!</p>
<p>I could keep myself up all night and into tomorrow by listing different groups of royalty and the ways they scam the system.</p>
<p>&#8230;except "scam the system" is a misnomer.  I am not listing defects in a perfectable system.  I am <i>describing</i> the system.</p>
<p>It is corrupt, corrupt, corrupt.  From Ted Kennedy who killed a woman and yet is toasted as a "lion of liberalism", to George Bush who did his share of party drugs (and my share, and your share, and your share&#8230;) while young yet let other youngsters rot in jail for the exact same excesses instead of waving his royal wand of pardoning, to thousand of well-paid NSA employees who put the Stasi to shame in their ruthless destruction of our rights, to the Silicon Valley CEOs who buy vacation houses with the money they make forging and selling chains to Fort Meade, to every single bastard at RSA who <a href="http://www.theverge.com/2013/12/20/5231006/nsa-paid-10-million-for-a-back-door-into-rsa-encryption-according-to">had a hand in taking the thirty pieces of silver</a>, to the three star generals who routinely screw subordinates and get away with it (even as sergeants are given dishonorable discharges for the same thing), to the MIT cops and Massachusetts prosecutor who drove Aaron Swartz to suicide, to every drug court judge who sends 22 year olds to jail for pot&#8230;while high on Quaalude and vodka because she's got some fucking personal tragedy and no one understands her pain, to every cop who's anally raped a citizen under color of law, to every other cop who's intentionally triggered a "drug" dog because the guy looked guilty, to every politician who goes on moral crusades while barebacking prostitutes and money laundering the payments, to every teacher who retired at age 60 on 80% salary, to every cop who has 50 state concealed carry even while the serfs are disarmed, to every politician, judge, or editorial-writer who has ever used the phrase "first amendment zone" non-ironically: this is how the system is designed to work.</p>
<p>The system is not fixable because it is not broken.  It is <b>working</b>, 24 hours a day, 365 days a year, to give the insiders their royal prerogatives, and to shove the regulations, the laws, and the debt up the asses of everyone else.</p>
<p>Burn it to the ground.</p>
<p>Burn it to the ground.</p>
<p>Burn it to the ground.</p>
<p>Merry Christmas.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/23/burn-the-fucking-system-to-the-ground/">Burn the Fucking System to the Ground</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
 <img src="http://www.popehat.com/?feed-stats-post-id=21266" width="1" height="1" style="display: none;" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/23/burn-the-fucking-system-to-the-ground/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>416</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/23/burn-the-fucking-system-to-the-ground/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Ten Points About Speech, Ducks, And Flights To Africa</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Popehat/~3/Cn328vTYzDo/</link>
		<comments>http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/21/ten-points-about-speech-ducks-and-flights-to-africa/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 21 Dec 2013 22:32:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ken White]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Politics & Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Free Speech]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.popehat.com/?p=21244</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[1. The First Amendment protects you from government sanction, either directly (by criminal prosecution) or indirectly (when someone uses the government's laws and the courts to punish you, as in a defamation action). It is currently in vogue to exclaim "NOBODY IS ARGUING OTHERWISE" when someone makes this point. Bullshit. People are consistently saying that [&#8230;]<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/21/ten-points-about-speech-ducks-and-flights-to-africa/">Ten Points About Speech, Ducks, And Flights To Africa</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>1.  The First Amendment protects you from government sanction, either directly (by criminal prosecution) or indirectly (when someone uses the government's laws and the courts to punish you, as in a defamation action).  It is currently in vogue to exclaim "NOBODY IS ARGUING OTHERWISE" when someone makes this point.  Bullshit.  People are consistently saying that private action (like criticism, or firings) violates the First Amendment, either directly or through <a href="http://politicalticker.blogs.cnn.com/2013/12/19/jindal-palin-duck-dynasty-star-suspended-over-intolerance-of-politically-correct/" target="_blank">sloppy implication.</a>  Promoting ignorance about our most important rights is a bad thing that we should call out, even when we're currently upset about something.  Our rights are under constant assault on multiple fronts, and when we encourage citizens to misunderstand them we make it easier for the government to whittle them away.  </p>
<p>2.  The phrase "the spirit of the First Amendment" often signals approaching nonsense.  So, regrettably, does the phrase "free speech" when uncoupled from constitutional free speech principles.  These terms often smuggle unprincipled and internally inconsistent concepts &#8212; like the doctrine of the Preferred+ First Speaker.  The doctrine of the Preferred First Speaker holds that when Person A speaks, listeners B, C, and D should refrain from their full range of constitutionally protected expression to preserve the ability of Person A to speak without fear of non-governmental consequences that Person A doesn't like.  The doctrine of the Preferred First Speaker applies different levels of scrutiny and judgment to the first person who speaks and the second person who reacts to them; it asks "why was it necessary for you to say that" or "what was your motive in saying that" or "did you consider how that would impact someone" to the second person and not the first.  It's ultimately incoherent as a theory of freedom of expression.</p>
<p>3.  Notwithstanding #2, the concepts of proportionality, community, dialogue, love, charity, grace, empathy, forgiveness, humility, and self-awareness are all values decent people ought to apply to a discussion.  They aren't about free speech or the First Amendment; they are about humanity.  They are more powerful and convincing when applied consistently &#8212; when you do not demand grace of others than you aren't willing to extend yourself.  That doesn't happen much.</p>
<p>4.  The marketplace of ideas assigns consequences to all participants.  That means, for instance, that A&#038;E might suffer market consequences for its behavior.  That's a feature, not a bug.</p>
<p>5.  A substantial percentage of outrage is bullshit.  So is a substantial percentage of outrage about outrage, and so on.  Outrage is often about consolidating political power and promoting the view that your political opponents are horrible people.  Much of the dialogue about Mr. Robertson being suspended from A&#038;E consists of partisans eager to use the opportunity to argue that (1) people like Mr. Robertson are horrible people or (2) people who criticize Mr. Robertson are horrible people.  Outrage is often an occasion for "THIS JUST PROVES WHAT I AM ALWAYS SAYING ABOUT THEM," with the particular case a thin disguise.  Yes, when I do it, too.</p>
<p>6.  Companies make decisions about hiring and firing based on both money and company culture.  Sometimes these decisions are "right" in the sense that the decisions accurately predict what outcome will please the most customers and advertisers and keep revenues up.  Sometimes the decisions are New Coke.  Often the stated reasons for the decisions are hypocritical bullshit, as in the case of A&#038;E.  That's the way it works.  Discussions about corporate decisions in the wake of controversy are dominated by (1) people who normally excoriate corporate decision-making but suddenly applaud it when the outcome suits their political beliefs, and (2) people who normally celebrate the market and promote the privilege of corporate decision-making but suddenly find it unpalatable when it produces a result that offends their politics.  Some of the people applauding A&#038;E are people who last week were furious at the concept that companies have First Amendment rights.  Some of the people trying to conflate A&#038;E and the government are people who last week were vigorously arguing that companies should not have to insure birth control if it offends their religious sensibilities.</p>
<p>7.  Bad behavior is not a zero-sum game.  If a person is a public relations executive, and identifies themselves as their employer's public relations executive on their Twitter account, and then uses that Twitter account associated with their employer's name in a way you'd use a private account &#8212; being edgy, vulgar, saying things that might offend people, and what have you &#8212; then they are bad at public relations and doing their employer a disservice.  Being a corporation's public relations executive is not a vehicle for self-expression.  But if people offer a wildly disproportionate, unmerciful, un-empathetic, graceless, ugly response &#8212; like the hashtag #HasJustineLandedYet, salivating over knowing the precise moment someone learns she has been fired for her very stupid behavior &#8212; then they are still deplorable.  The bad judgment of the PR executive does not diminish the deplorable behavior of the voyeurs, and the deplorable behavior of the voyeurs does not diminish the very bad judgment of the PR executive.     </p>
<p>8.  The fact that a viewpoint is contained in your holy book does not insulate it from criticism.  The fact that a viewpoint is part of a person's faith tradition might lead you to consider proportionality, love, charity, grace, empathy, forgiveness, humility, and self-awareness in framing a response to it.  On the other hand, it's reasonable to exercise proportionality, love, charity, grace, empathy, forgiveness, humility, and self-awareness in thinking about how your faith doctrines make other people feel.  "You're going to Hell, but you shouldn't be offended when I say so, because it's in my holy book," is not a cunning argument.  Also:  maybe there's someone who is consistent about <em>all</em> holy books when arguing "you should cut them a break because it's in their holy book," but I personally have not met this person.  </p>
<p>9.  Most major American political groups participate in the politics of outrage and the tactic of "look how this person represents Their Side."  Maybe there's someone capable of a principled empirical analysis of who does it more, but I doubt it.  I don't trust your gut about who does it more, and you shouldn't trust mine.      </p>
<p>10.  You have no right to be free of offense.  You also have no right to be free of people telling you that you are offensive.  You only have a right to govern how you will react. </p>
<p>I'm on hiatus.  I hope to be back in January.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/21/ten-points-about-speech-ducks-and-flights-to-africa/">Ten Points About Speech, Ducks, And Flights To Africa</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
 <img src="http://www.popehat.com/?feed-stats-post-id=21244" width="1" height="1" style="display: none;" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/21/ten-points-about-speech-ducks-and-flights-to-africa/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>180</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/21/ten-points-about-speech-ducks-and-flights-to-africa/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Clark's Favorite Books Part 1: Science Fiction</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Popehat/~3/La1PTh-AtVk/</link>
		<comments>http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/21/clarks-favorite-books-part-1-science-fiction/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 21 Dec 2013 22:10:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Clark]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Books]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.popehat.com/?p=21255</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Patrick has been bugging me recently for my top 10 books list. I'm an anarchist, and I don't kowtow to The Man, maaan, so I refuse to generate a top ten list. On the other hand, I can't resist telling people what cool shit they should be reading, so here's my I'm-not-even-sure-how-large list of books [&#8230;]<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/21/clarks-favorite-books-part-1-science-fiction/">Clark's Favorite Books Part 1: Science Fiction</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Patrick has been bugging me recently for my top 10 books list.  I'm an anarchist, and I don't kowtow to The Man, <i>maaan</i>, so I refuse to generate a top ten list.  On the other hand, I can't resist telling people what cool shit they should be reading, so here's my I'm-not-even-sure-how-large list of books that I really like.  Is it my "top" list?  I dunno.  I'm not the viewpoint character in High Fidelity; I don't spend that much time rank ordering stuff.  Make of this list (these lists) what you will.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Lucifers-Hammer-Larry-Niven-ebook/dp/B004478DOU?tag=popehat-20"><br />
  <img border=0 src="http://www.popehat.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/lucifers_hammer.jpg" style="float:left; margin:10px; width:250px;"/><br />
</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B004478DOU?tag=popehat-20">Lucifer's Hammer</a> &#8211; this is, IMO, the single best post apocalyptic / survival book ever written.  It's got it all: astronomy,	physics, chemistry, economics, individual survival skills, sociology.  One mark of a good book is whether you remember scenes from it years later. LH has dozens.  It's a little bit dated by now (US / USSR Cold War, post-Vietnam US Army with racial integration problems, etc.), but it's still a great yarn.</p>
<div style="clear:both;"></div>
<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Mote-Gods-Eye-ebook/dp/B004YDL2CY?tag=popehat-20"><br />
  <img border=0 src="http://www.popehat.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/mote.jpg" style="float:left; margin:10px; width:250px;"/><br />
</a></p>
<p><b><a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B004YDL2CY?tag=popehat-20">The Mote in God's Eye</a></b> &#8211; Niven and Pournelle are off to an early lead.  TMiGE is the single best First Contact story ever written, and it deals with aliens that are truly weird, in some ways, and truly familiar in others.  It warrants the term "space opera" for working at a grand scale: grand scales of space, time, imaginary physics, and stakes to human life.</p>
<div style="clear:both;"></div>
<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Snow-Crash-Neal-Stephenson-ebook/dp/B000FBJCJE?tag=popehat-20"><br />
  <img border=0 src="http://www.popehat.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/snowcrash.jpg" style="float:left; margin:10px; width:250px;"/><br />
</a></p>
<p><b><a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B000FBJCJE?tag=popehat-20">Snowcrash</a></b> &#8211; Neal Stephenson has written better books (Cryptonomicon, Anathem), but he's never written a more-Neal-Stephenson-per-page book than Snowcrash. It distilled, parodied, and reified the cyberpunk genre.  As with Lucifer's Hammer, it was so good that it basically took all of the air out of the genre.  After this, what's left to do?  Does it have Big Ideas(tm)?  And how.  Dropping Big Idea bombs always runs the risk of looking silly, but with out risk there is no art.  Shows its age a bit, but still excellent.</p>
<div style="clear:both;"></div>
<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Moon-Harsh-Mistress-Robert-Heinlein/dp/0312863551?tag=popehat-20"><br />
  <img border=0 src="http://www.popehat.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/miahm.jpg" style="float:left; margin:10px; width:250px;"/><br />
</a></p>
<p><b><a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/0312863551?tag=popehat-20">The Moon is a Harsh Mistress</a></b> &#8211; Heinlein distilled mid 20th century science fiction. Everything either good or bad in it, he did better or worse than others.  Likable characters?  And how.  Embarrassing authorial excess?  Yep.  TMiaHM shows him at his best: fast paced, emotionally moving, exciting, full of ideas, and very little of the embarrassing or weird Heinlein.  It's a seminal libertarian / anarcho capitalist science fiction novel and created the mold for a half dozen other similar novels that came later.  The ending still leaves me a bit melancholy even thirty years after I first read it.</p>
<div style="clear:both;"></div>
<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Anathem-Neal-Stephenson-ebook/dp/B0015DPXKI?tag=popehat-20"><br />
  <img border=0 src="http://www.popehat.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/anathem1.jpg" style="float:left; margin:10px; width:250px;"/><br />
</a></p>
<p><b><a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B0015DPXKI?tag=popehat-20">Anathem</a></b> &#8211; Stephenson pulls forward and ties for first place.  (I'm reminded of the beginning of the movie Rounders: science fiction isn't a game of luck; it's a game of skill.  Do you think that Stephenson and Niven and Pournelle keep writing great novels because they're <i>lucky</i>?).  Anathem has it all: deep history, parallel worlds, medieval monasteries, formal logic, quantum uncertainty, cross-polar chase scenes, orbital mechanics, starships.  A lot of people say that they thought that Anathem was too wordy or too weird.  I feel bad for them &#8211; they've admitted something very embarrassing about themselves in public.</p>
<div style="clear:both;"></div>
<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Fire-Upon-Deep-Zones-Thought-ebook/dp/B000FBJAGO?tag=popehat-20"><br />
  <img border=0 src="http://www.popehat.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/fud.jpg" style="float:left; margin:10px; width:250px;"/><br />
</a></p>
<p><b><a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B000FBJAGO?tag=popehat-20">A Fire Upon the Deep</a></b> / <b><a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B002H8ORKM?tag=popehat-20">A Deepness in the Sky</a></b> &#8211; A lot of my favorite authors write very little&#8230;or, rather, they release very few books.  Mrs. Clark has a theory that authors accumulate good ideas for stories at a certain fixed rate, and their first books drain the tank half dry.  According to her elaboration of this theory, most authors have two or three good books in them.  I disagree with this hard-line version, but I think that there's some truth in the idea.  Specifically, I think that most authors can write a good novel only once every few years (or, rather, most authors can't write a good novel at all, and those that can write one at all can write one at most every few years).  Anyway, Vernor Vinge, computer science professor, does the smart thing: he writes at exactly the rate that he can generate good stories.  Sadly, this means he doesn't write might.  The two novels referenced here contain a lot: space exploration, vast galactic civilizations, weird physics, thoughts on anarchy, trade, and fascism.</p>
<div style="clear:both;"></div>
<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Star-Fraction-Fall-Revolution-ebook/dp/B00CK5ATJK?tag=popehat-20"><br />
  <img border=0 src="http://www.popehat.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/starfraction.jpg" style="float:left; margin:10px; width:250px;"/><br />
</a></p>
<p><b><a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00CK5ATJK?tag=popehat-20">The Star Fraction</a> / <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00CK5ATK4?tag=popehat-20">The Stone Canal</a> / <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00CBFXM8Y?tag=popehat-20">The Cassini Division</a> / <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00CBFXNBA?tag=popehat-20">The Sky Road</a></b> &#8211; There are only three important things in life: what is the point of existence and what is The Good?  what is worth having or doing?, when those things are scarce, how should they be divided up?  Or, in shorter form: religion, politics, and money.  You know &#8211; the three things that we're not supposed to talk about with people.  In the mid 1980s the Scottish Big Three exploded on the American science fiction scene: Ian Banks (RIP), Ken Macleod, and Charlie Stross.  Stross flamed out after a few good books (see Mrs. Clark's rule of thumb about most authors having only a few good books).  Banks is operatic, utopian, and excellent.  Macleod, though&#8230;Macleod is something between the sleeper of the group and the tortoise that wins the race.  He's not as operatic as Banks &#8211; one novel (Newton's Wake) aside, there are no vast mega-structures, few vast spaceships, not much wit in each paragraph&#8230;but he does consistently talk about the big three topics: what is the good?  what are things worth?  who should divide them up?  He's not a perfect writer &#8211; far too many of his novels have a denouement that boils down to several Scottish (just like him!)  reformed Trotskyists (just like him!) discussing politics in a pub (just like him!), but he's good.  The four books listed here aren't a series per se &#8211; more like riffing on the same subject via different paths (see also: Goldberg Variations, Kim Stanley Robinson's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Three_Californias_Trilogy">Three California's Trilogy</a>, George Bush and Barrack Obama, etc.  They're all worth reading.</p>
<div style="clear:both;"></div>
<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Directive-Novel-Daybreak-John-Barnes-ebook/dp/B0030CVRZW?tag=popehat-20"><br />
  <img border=0 src="http://www.popehat.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/directive51.jpg" style="float:left; margin:10px; width:250px;"/><br />
</a></p>
<p><b><a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B0030CVRZW?tag=popehat-20">Directive 51</a></b> &#8211; To my mind, the two most underrated science fiction authors of the last 10 or 20 years are Walter Jon Williams and John Barnes.  Both have technical mastery of fiction writing, good characterization, amazing plots, complexity, and a dozen other skills down <i>cold</i>.  They're not the only authors who are this good &#8211; there are a half dozen or so now writing who perform at this level.  The amazing thing, though, is that these guys are all but invisible.  Their works should be classics, and yet they're outsold by Jim Butcher, John Scalzi, and Stephenie Meyer.  So, short version: pick up absolutely anything by either of these two guys (aside from Barne's Jak Jinnaka series, which was sort sort of experiment that didn't work for me).  Anyway, on to Directive 51.  This is the first book in a trilogy that traces the breakdown of our current world into a post apocalyptic nightmare.  In our hyper-connected early 21st century society memes grow and spread like flashmobs, and soon a semiotics researcher named Arnie Yang (John Barne's not-really-a-Mary-Sue-but-sorta-based-on-himself) starts to see dangerous resonances.  Deep Greens are talking about crashing the system and returning to nature.  Billionaires are talking about crashing the system and returning to <a href="http://unqualified-reservations.blogspot.com">monarchy</a>.  Techies are talking about crashing the system with nanotech.  What the heck is going on?  The book is a multi-viewpoint-architected novel like a big technothriller (c.f. The Hunt for Red October, etc.) that investigates this question from a variety of viewpoints.  Unfortunately, almost as soon as the authorities detect that something is wrong, the disaster is upon them:  nanotech starts destroying modern technology, and the good guys are always two steps behind&#8230;or three.   One of the hardest things in fiction is creating a true sense of dread and foreboding: most of the time we're watching a TV show or reading a book, we know that everything is going to turn out all right in the end.  Luke will blow up the Deathstar.  Doctor House will cure the patient.  Professor Bernardo de la Plaz will free the Loonies from Earth's fascist grip.  Barnes isn't like that.  Good people die, and at every step of the way you fear that the good guys could lose entirely&#8230;and the scenes <i>stick</i>.  More than a decade after reading Kaleidoscope Century I remember the protagonist throwing gold coins into the air to precipitate a riot and years after reading Directive 51 I remember a scene of captives being fast-marched past terrified viewpoint characters who are hiding in a crumbling suburb.  After all this time these bits still send chills down my spine.  Anyway, read Directive 51&#8230;and look out for a group review I've got queued up entitled "Three Post Apocalypses, Left, Right, and Center" that covers John Varley's Slow Apocalypse (left), S.M. Stirling's Dies the Fire (right) and Barnes' Directive 51 (center).  I've got some thoughts on <i>in <s>vino</s> post apocalypse veritas</i>.</p>
<div style="clear:both;"></div>
<p><b>update</b>: added 23 December 2013:</p>
<div style="clear:both;"></div>
<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/0312874561?tag=popehat-20"></a><br />
  <img border=0 src="http://www.popehat.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/dying_earth.jpg" style="float:left; margin:10px; width:250px;"/></p>
<p>
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/0312874561?tag=popehat-20"></a>Tales of the Dying Earth &#8211; There's a genre that I don't read or watch, "comedy of manners", which &#8211; Wikipedia tells me &#8211; satirizes  the manners and affectations of a social class or of multiple classes, often represented by stereotypical stock characters. As far as I can tell examples of it mostly occur in mid-century British novels and TV, and a few American books making fun of NYC socialites.  Neither is something that I'm particularly interested in, but I've been provided entre to the genre by Jack Vance, who writes utterly hilarious science fantasy that says a lot more about human foibles than it does about what the world will look like 30,000 years from now.  In Vance's Dying Earth series the swollen red sun is so tired and ancient that it may go out at any time, and all of the characters in his books (a) realize this, and (b) react to it either with beyond-cinematic arrogance, beyond-Roissy rakishness, or beyong Quentin Crisp flamboyant good cheer.  If you picture the characters Thundar the Barbarian as voiced by Jeeves and Wooster you'd not be too far off course (fictional exempli gratia "let me slip out of this wet pit of eternal despond and into a dry martini!").  A decade or more after reading it I still occassionally pause in the middle of the day and laugh thinking about Cugel as an incompetent worminger, or his insoucience in eating from the expensive buffet at the company town associated with a dragon scale mine.  Fun, light reading, but really <i>really</i> rewarding.
</p>
<div style="clear:both;"></div>
<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B001QL5MAA?tag=popehat-20"><br />
  <img border=0 src="http://www.popehat.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/rev_space.jpg" style="float:left; margin:10px; width:250px;"/><br />
</a></p>
<p>
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B001QL5MAA?tag=popehat-20">Revelation Space</a> /<br />
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B000OIZUH6?tag=popehat-20">Chasm City</a> /<br />
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B001LFDABO?tag=popehat-20">Redemption Ark</a> /<br />
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B001ODO61G?tag=popehat-20">Absolution Gap</a> /<br />
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B0015DYJY4?tag=popehat-20">The Prefect</a> &#8211; Wikipedia calls Alastair Reynolds a writer of "dark hard science fiction".  I think that's a perfect term.  The "Revelation Space" universe he crafts is cold, unforgiving, and vaguely menacing.  Not just vaguely menacing in a "Cold Equations" / "there's nothing between my skin and the deadly vacuum but this thin suit" manner, but in a "there are deep and impersonal forces that are none-the-less malevolent and either actively want you dead, or at least won't care a bit if you die" sense.  Couple that with rigorous physics, tight plots, and a very intricate back story and a deeply thought out universe, and the books are a mix of wonder at how much mankind might achieve over the next 500 years despite no magic get-out-of-jail-free cards like FTL, and a sense of dread about just how cold and scary the universe is.  Picture Iain Banks without the cheerful tone and with more hard physics, and you get something a lot like Alastair Reynolds.
</p>
<div style="clear:both;"></div>
<p>If you liked these reviews, keep your eyes peeled for future installments:</p>
<ul>
<li>Clark's Favorite Books Part 2: Fantasy
	</li>
<li>Clark's Favorite Books Part 3: Politics
	</li>
<li>Clark's Favorite Books Part 4: Miscellaneous
</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/21/clarks-favorite-books-part-1-science-fiction/">Clark's Favorite Books Part 1: Science Fiction</a> © 2007-2013 by the authors of <a href="http://www.popehat.com">Popehat</a>. This feed is for personal, non-commercial use only. Using this feed on any other site is a copyright violation. No scraping.</p>
 <img src="http://www.popehat.com/?feed-stats-post-id=21255" width="1" height="1" style="display: none;" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/21/clarks-favorite-books-part-1-science-fiction/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>163</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://www.popehat.com/2013/12/21/clarks-favorite-books-part-1-science-fiction/</feedburner:origLink></item>
	</channel>
</rss>
